Katie Louchheim Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Katie Louchheim Papers 1906-1991 1942-1968
MSS50559
Louchheim, Katie, 1903-
32,000 items
81 containers plus 1 classified and 25 oversize
35 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
United States deputy assistant secretary of state, Democratic Party official, author, and public speaker. Journals, family papers, correspondence, memoranda, reports, lists, speeches, interviews, drafts of writings, scrapbooks, photographs, newspaper clippings, and other printed matter documenting Louchheim's public service and leadership in the Democratic Party.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Annenberg, Walter H., 1908-2002--Correspondence.; Bingham, Barry, 1906-1988--Correspondence.; Bingham, Mary Caperton, 1904- --Correspondence.; Boggs, Hale, 1914-1972--Correspondence.; Boggs, Lindy, 1916-2013--Correspondence.; Bruce, Evangeline--Correspondence.; Butler, Paul M. (Paul Mulholland), 1905-1961.; Carlisle, Kitty, 1910-2007--Interviews.; Carpenter, Liz.; Cerf, Bennett, 1898-1971--Correspondence.; Douglas, William O. (William Orville), 1898-1980.; Duke, Angier Biddle, 1915-1995--Correspondence.; Duke, Robin Chandler Lynn--Correspondence.; Edwards, India--Correspondence.; Ehrlich, Henry--Correspondence.; Furness, Betty, 1916-1994--Interviews.; Gore, Albert, 1907-1998--Correspondence.; Gore, Pauline La Fon--Correspondence.; Harriman, Florence Jaffray, 1870-1967--Correspondence.; Humphrey, Hubert H. (Hubert Horatio), 1911-1978--Correspondence.; Johnson, Lady Bird, 1912-2007--Correspondence.; Johnson, Lady Bird, 1912-2007.; Johnson, Lyndon B. (Lyndon Baines), 1908-1973.; Kennedy, John F. (John Fitzgerald), 1917-1963.; Kennedy, Robert F., 1925-1968.; Louchheim family.; Louchheim, Katie, 1903-1991.; Louchheim, Walter C. (Walter Clinton), 1899-1973. Walter C. Louchheim papers.; McCarthy, Abigail Q. (Abigail Quigley)--Correspondence.; McCarthy, Eugene J., 1916-2005--Correspondence.; Mitchell, Stephen A. (Stephen Arnold), 1903-1974--Correspondence.; Motley, Constance Baker, 1921-2005--Interviews.; Rayburn, Sam, 1882-1961--Correspondence.; Reischauer, Edwin O. (Edwin Oldfather), 1910-1990--Correspondence.; Reischauer, Haru Matsukata, 1915- --Correspondence.; Reston, James, 1909-1995; Rusk, Dean, 1909-1994.; Schofield family.; Scofield, Adele Joseph. Adele Joseph Scofield papers.; Sorensen, Theodore C.; Stevenson, Adlai E. (Adlai Ewing), 1900-1965.; Truman, Bess Wallace--Correspondence.; Truman, Harry S., 1884-1972.; Wyzanski, Charles E., Jr. (Charles Edward), 1906-1986--Correspondence.
Organizations
Democratic National Committee (U.S.); Democratic Party (U.S.); United Nations Monetary and Financial Conference (1944: Bretton Woods, N.H.); United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration.; United States. Bureau of Educational and Cultural Affairs.; United States. Department of State. Bureau of Public Affairs.; United States. Department of State. Office of Community Advisory Services.
Subjects
Landscape protection.; Women's rights.; Women--Political activity--United States.
Places
United States--Foreign relations--1945-1989.; United States--Politics and government--1945-1989.; Washington (D.C.)--Social life and customs.
Occupations
Authors.; Public officials.
Acquisition Information
The papers of Katie Louchheim, United States deputy assistant secretary of state, Democratic Party official, author, and public speaker, were given to the Library of Congress by Louchheim between 1973 and 1986. Additions were given by her daughter, Judith Louchheim Read, in 1991 and 1994. Opera libretti with accompanying correspondence were transferred to the Manuscript Division from the Library of Congress Copyright Office in 1976.
Transfers
Items have been transferred from the Manuscript Division to other custodial divisions of the Library. Some photographs have been transferred to the Prints and Photographs Division. Audio recordings have been transferred to the Motion Picture, Broadcasting, and Recorded Sound Division. All transfers are identified in these divisions as part of the Katie Louchheim Papers.
Access and Restrictions
Restrictions apply governing the use, photoduplication, or publication of items in this collection. Consult reference staff in the Manuscript Division for information concerning these restrictions. In addition, many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Security Classified Documents
Government regulations control the use of security classified material in this collection. Manuscript Division staff can furnish information concerning access to and use of classified items.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1903, Dec. 28 Born, New York, N.Y.
1921 Graduated, Rosemary Hall, Greenwich, Conn.
1926 Married Walter C. Louchheim
1926 1927 Attended Columbia University, New York, N.Y.
1945 1946 Assistant to the director of public information, United Nations Relief and Recovery Administration
1945 Special assignment to displaced persons camps, Germany
1948 Delegate from the District of Columbia, Democratic National Convention, Philadelphia, Pa.
1949 Member, District of Columbia Democratic Party Central Committee
1949 1952 Coauthor, For Women Only column, Labor's League for Political Education
1952 Delegate from the District of Columbia and platform committee member, Democratic National Convention, Chicago, Ill.
1953 1956 Director for women's activities, Democratic National Committee
1956 1960 Vice chairman, Democratic National Committee
1956 1961 Democratic Party national committeewoman, District of Columbia
1961 1962 Special assistant on women's affairs, State Department
1962 1963 Deputy assistant secretary of state for public affairs, State Department
1963 1966 Deputy assistant secretary of state for community advisory services, State Department
1966 Published With or Without Roses. Garden City, N.Y.: Doubleday and Co.
1966 1968 Deputy assistant secretary of state for educational and cultural affairs, State Department
1968 1969 United States ambassador, Unesco
1970 Published By the Political Sea. Garden City, N.Y.: Doubleday and Co.
1971 1973 Contributor, Washington Post and Christian Science Monitor
1983 Published The Making of the New Deal. Cambridge, Mass.: Harvard University Press
1991, Feb. 11 Died, New York, N.Y.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Kathleen Scofield (“Katie”) Louchheim (1903-1991) span the years 1906-1991, with the bulk of material dating from 1942 to 1968. The collection documents Louchheim's prominence in Democratic Party politics, including her tenure as vice chairman of the Democratic National Committee from 1956 to 1960, and her Department of State appointments as deputy assistant secretary for public affairs, 1962-1963, community advisory services, 1963-1966, and educational and cultural affairs, 1966-1968. The collection includes family papers, general correspondence, journals, social calendars, subject files, interviews, speeches and writings, photographs, memorabilia, and scrapbooks arranged in eleven series: Family Papers, General Correspondence, Subject File, Speeches and Writings, Scrapbooks, 1978 Addition, 1986 Addition, 1997 Addition, 2010 Addition, Classified, and Oversize.
The Family Papers consist largely of letters to and from family members and include some of the collection's earliest letters from Louchheim, largely to her husband, Walter C. Louchheim, and mother, Adele Joseph Scofield, between 1926 and 1961. The series also contains letters from Walter Louchheim while attending the Bretton Woods Conference in 1944. The papers of Adele Joseph Scofield reflect her numerous charitable activities and interest in politics.
The General Correspondence series documents Louchheim's involvement in Democratic Party activities, her State Department tenure, and the social life of Washington, D.C. Correspondents include Barry Bingham, Mary Caperton Bingham, Hale Boggs, Lindy Boggs, Bennett Cerf, Albert Gore (1907-1998), Pauline La Fon Gore, Florence Jaffray Hurst Harriman, Hubert H. Humphery, Lady Bird Johnson, Abigail Q. McCarthy, Eugene J. McCarthy, Stephen A. Mitchell, Sam Rayburn, Edwin O. Reischauer, Haru Matsukata Reischauer, Bess Wallace Truman, and Charles E. Wyzanski. There are also personal notes from presidents Harry S. Truman, John F. Kennedy, and Lyndon B. Johnson and from Adlai E. Stevenson (1900-1965).
The Subject File concerns positions held by Louchheim with the Democratic National Committee and the State Department as well as her association with various committees and organizations. The largest segment pertains to her years at the State Department from 1961 to 1968 and details her involvement with special welfare projects abroad, her endeavors to enlist the interest and support of women and women's organizations in international cultural affairs, her efforts to increase contact between the department and the American public, and her oversight of community relations with foreign visitors, exchange programs, foreign student affairs, and foreign service specialist programs.
Material in the Subject File relating to the Democratic National Committee provides insight into grassroots and national politics, especially women's activities. The series also concerns Louchheim's postwar work with displaced persons and refugees with the United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration (UNRRA) and her membership on Lady Bird Johnson's Committee for a More Beautiful Capital during the 1960s. Other information on the UNRRA can be found in the Speeches and Writings and the Family Papers series.
The Speech and Writings series includes drafts and publicity copies of speeches, correspondence, travel arrangements, press releases, and clippings. Included are speeches delivered by Louchheim for the Democratic National Committee and for Democratic candidates throughout the country. Her speeches on behalf of the State Department explore aspects of official policies, women's activities, volunteer programs, beautification projects, foreign affairs, educational and cultural programs, and the department's activities at home and abroad. In foreign countries, Louchheim was called upon most frequently to speak about the status, employment, and rights of American women.
Many of Louchheim's published and unpublished writings relate to social and political life of the nation's capital. "Protocol in Washington," an unpublished book-length manuscript, includes interview material with prominent Washington hostesses of the late 1940s. Her political memoirs were published as By the Political Sea. Several short stories and plays further explore the interplay between Washington's social and political life. The series also includes Louchheim's poetry, most notably a collection published under the title, With or Without Roses. Correspondence from publishers, editors, fans, critics, and friends in the publishing field is also included.
The 1978 and 1986 Additions contain family papers, general correspondence, subject files, and speeches and writings. Many of the same correspondents listed in the General Correspondence and Subject File series, including Walter H. Annenberg, Evangeline Bruce, Angier Biddle Duke, Robin Chandler Lynn Duke, India Edwards, and Henry Ehrlich, can be found in these series as well. Also included are files on Louchheim's work in the State Department, Unesco, and UNRRA, as well as some of her speeches and writings. The 1986 Addition contains photographs and additional scrapbooks.
The 1997 Addition includes journals kept by Louchheim from 1942 to 1981 describing life in wartime Washington, Democratic Party campaigns and conventions during the 1950s and 1960s, and Louchheim's State Department positions. Her descriptions of Washington's social and political life constitute the largest part of the journals. The volumes, many of which include partial indexes, contain accounts of political figures, many of whom were Louchheim's close friends. Frequently mentioned and quoted are Paul M. Butler, Liz Carpenter, William O. Douglas, Albert Gore (1907-1998), Florence Jaffray Hurst Harriman, Hubert H. Humphrey, Lyndon B. Johnson, Lady Bird Johnson, John F. Kennedy, Robert F. Kennedy, Eugene J. McCarthy, James Reston, Dean Rusk, Theodore Sorensen, Adlai E. Stevenson, and Harry S. Truman. Interviews conducted by Louchheim in 1985 and 1986 for a book on prominent women include Kitty Carlisle, Betty Furness, and Constance Baker Motley. The 2010 Addition consists of political campaign buttons and other memorabilia.
Organization of the Papers
The collection is arranged in eleven series:
Family Papers, 1912-1974
General Correspondence, 1918-1974
Subject File, circa 1934-1974
Speeches and Writings File, circa 1937-1974
Scrapbooks, 1945-1974
1978 Addition, 1942-1977
1986 Addition, 1906-1985
1997 Addition, 1942-1991
2010 Addition, 1940-1976
Classified, 1944-1970
Oversize, 1945-1974
Container List
- Family Papers, 1912-1974 (Box 1-2)
  Correspondence and printed matter to, from, and about family members.
  Arranged alphabetically by name, topic, or type of material and therein chronologically.
  - Louchheim, Katie (Box 1)
    - Correspondence
      - Joseph, H. Oscar, 1938-1952
      - Kauffman, Frederick M., 1942-1945
      - Louchheim, Dene and Stuart F., 1962-1967
      - Louchheim, Mary (daughter), 1950 See also same container, Louchheim, Walter C., 1945
      - Louchheim, Walter C. (husband), 1944-1961, undated, (9 folders)
      - Miscellaneous family members, circa 1936-1964
      - Scofield, Adele Joseph (mother), 1936-1938, (2 folders)
      - Sifton, Judith Louchheim (daughter), 1971 See also same container, Louchheim, Walter C., 1945
    - Marriage to Walter C. Louchheim, 1926
  - Louchheim, Walter C., general correspondence, 1918-1919, 1939-1968, undated (Box 2)
  - Miscellany, 1912, 1924-1940, 1947, 1968-1972, undated
  - Scofield, Adele Joseph
    - Charitable activities on behalf of juvenile cardiac patients
      - Correspondence and drafts of writings, 1924-1930
      - Printed matter, 1915-1931, undated
    - Correspondence
      - Concerning death of Frederick Joseph, 1931
      - From
        - Louchheim, Katie, 1926-1932, 1946-1955, undated, (4 folders)
        - Louchheim, Walter C., 1926-1928, circa 1947-1948, undated
      - Miscellaneous, 1918, 1925-1937, 1946-1947, 1974, undated
    - Trip to Spain, 1927
- General Correspondence, 1918-1974 (Box 3-8)
  Letters received and copies of letters sent.
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent and therein chronologically.
  - Abell, Bess and Tyler, 1964-1968 (Box 3)
  - Abrahams, H. B., 1946-1970
  - Allen, James, 1943-1963
  - “A” miscellaneous, 1945-1969
  - Bayh, Birch and Marvella, 1962-1972, undated
  - Benton, William, 1968-1970
  - Bingham, Barry and Mary Caperton, 1953-1974
  - Blatt, Genevieve, 1959-1972
  - Boggs, Hale and Lindy, 1960-1974
  - Bruce, Evangeline, 1963-1964, undated
  - “B” miscellaneous, 1923-1972, undated
  - Carpenter, Liz, 1963-1973, undated See also Classified, (2 folders)
  - Cerf, Bennett, 1924-1925, 1938, undated
  - Choate, Charles, 1941-1942
  - Cook, Donald, 1964-1965
  - “C” miscellaneous, 1953-1974, undated
  - Darlington, Charles J., 1943-1963 (Box 4)
  - Derr, Hume, 1935-1939
  - Dick, Jane W., 1956-1969
  - Douglas, Mercedes, Mildred, and William O., 1939-1964, undated
  - Dunbar, Doris and Spaulding, 1948-1964, undated
  - “D” miscellaneous, 1948-1966, undated
  - Edwards, India, 1952-1964
  - Eising, Robert, 1920-1925, 1942-1947
  - Ehrlich, Henry and Pauline, 1937-1967
  - “E” miscellaneous, 1947-1964, undated
  - Foster, Betty, 1950-1973
  - “F” miscellaneous, 1937-1969, undated
  - Gore, Albert (1907-1998) and Pauline, 1952-1966
  - Green, Edith, 1958-1961, 1970-1974
  - “G” miscellaneous, 1948-1967, undated
  - Harriman, Florence Jaffray Hurst, 1951-1967
  - Herzog, Arthur, 1919-1923 (Box 5)
  - Hiss, Alger and Priscilla, 1941-1949
  - Hiss, Catherine and Donald, 1947-1973, undated
  - Hornaday, Mary, 1942-1951
  - Humphrey, Hubert H., 1954-1974 See also Container 18, same heading, and Classified
  - Humphrey, Muriel, 1964-1971, undated
  - “H” miscellaneous, 1918-1969, undated
  - Isenbergh, Pearl, 1960
  - Johnson, Lady Bird, 1955-1974, undated See also Containers 20-21, same heading, (3 folders)
  - Johnson, Lyndon B., 1954-1971, undated See also Container 21, same heading, (2 folders)
  - “J” miscellaneous, 1942-1965, undated
  - Kennedy, John F., 1958-1969, undated See also Container 21, same heading (Box 6)
  - Kerr, Florence, 1958-1964
  - Kilgore, Lillian Avery, 1959-1964
  - “K” miscellaneous, 1950-1971, undated
  - Lamson, Roy, 1943-1962
  - Lehman, Herbert H., 1946-1968
  - Limmer, Ruth, 1971-1974
  - “L” miscellaneous, 1920-1971, undated
  - McCarthy, Abigail Q. and Eugene J., 1965-1972, undated
  - McGee, Gale W. and Loraine, 1963-1974, undated
  - Mitchell, Stephen A., 1953-1960, (3 folders)
  - “M” miscellaneous, circa 1921-1969, undated
  - Neuberger, Kirby, 1923-1924
  - “N” miscellaneous, circa 1921-1968, undated
  - Oppenheimer, George, 1926 (Box 7)
  - Osherman, Jack A., 1923-1925, undated
  - “O-Q” miscellaneous, 1943-1969, undated
  - Ragland, Martha, 1971-1973
  - Rayburn, Sam, 1954-1968
  - Reischauer, Edwin O. and Haru Matsukata, 1962-1973 See also Classified, (2 folders)
  - Robb, Charles and Lynda Johnson, 1964-1971
  - Roosevelt, Dorothy Kemp, 1942, 1961
  - Rosenwald, Edward J., 1922-1924, 1962
  - Rothschild, Eleanor, 1921-1922
  - “R” miscellaneous, 1924-1964, undated
  - Schram, Herman, 1923-1926
  - Shapiro, Evelyn and Karl, 1947-1965
  - Sturges-Jones, Elizabeth, 1953-1961
  - Sulzberger, C. L., 1938-1939, 1956
  - “S” miscellaneous, 1920-1969, undated
  - Truman, Bess Wallace, 1954-1973, undated (Box 8)
  - Truman, Harry S., 1955-1971 See also Container 37, same heading
  - “T” miscellaneous, 1942-1969, undated
  - Ullman, Frederic, 1924-1926, undated, (2 folders)
  - “V” miscellaneous, 1953-1961
  - Wolff, Margo H., 1964-1965
  - Woodward, Shirley and Stanley, 1956-1960
  - Wyzanski, Charles Edward, 1937-1974
  - “W-Z” miscellaneous, circa 1921-1969, undated
- Subject File, circa 1934-1974 (Box 8-40)
  Correspondence, memoranda, reports, lists, clippings, and printed material relating to the Democratic National Committee, State Department, and various committees and organizations.
  Arranged alphabetically by subject or type of material and therein chronologically.
  - Airlie Foundation conferences, Warrenton, Va., 1962-1967 (Box 8)
  - American National Red Cross, 1966-1969
  - American Women in Radio and Television, 1960-1968 (Box 9)
  - American Women's Activities in Germany Conference, Garmisch, Germany, 1965
  - Art in the Embassies Program, 1963-1968
  - Awards, honors, and certificates, 1962-1969
  - Beautification programs for the nation and Washington, D.C., 1965-1967
  - Cards and invitations, circa 1934-1960
  - Central Business District Association, Detroit, Mich., 1965-1967
  - Clippings
    - 1954-1965, (2 folders)
    - 1966-1973, (2 folders) (Box 10)
  - Committee to Rescue Italian Art, 1966-1967
  - Conference on Continuing Education for Women, New York, N.Y., 1968
  - Cosmopolitan Club, New York, N.Y., 1968-1972
  - Defense Advisory Committee on Women in the Services, 1962-1970, (2 folders)
  - Delta Sigma Theta sorority, 1966-1967
  - Democratic Central Committee of the District of Columbia
    - Clippings, 1948-1956
    - Correspondence, 1948-1961
    - Primaries, 1952-1956
  - Democratic Digest
    - 1941-1959, (2 folders)
    - 1960-1961 (Box 11)
  - Democratic National Committee
    - Activities, 1953, 1959-1961, 1970-1974, (2 folders)
    - Campaigns
      - Assistance offers, 1964
      - Lists, contacts, plans, and programs, 1964
      - Miscellany, 1955-1956
      - Trips, 1952, 1956
    - Change in vice chairman, 1960
    - Conventions
      - 1952, platform
      - 1956
        - Convention data and women delegates
        - Post-convention correspondence
      - 1960 (Box 12)
        - Campaign material, 1960-1961
        - Reports
    - District of Columbia home rule lobbying, 1959-1960
    - Fund-raising, 1940, 1960, (2 folders)
    - General correspondence, 1958-1959
    - Letters of appreciation and congratulations, 1954-1961
    - Lists of members, 1957-1967
    - News and Comments, newsletter, 1955-1958
    - Office of Women's Activities
      - Campaign, 1960
        - Notebook
        - Post-campaign material
      - Congratulatory letters, 1953, (2 folders) (Box 13)
      - Memoranda, activities, and reports, 1953-1958
      - Reports of director, 1955-1961
    - Policy Council, 1969-1970
    - Political background, 1952-1960
    - Publicity, statements on women, 1957-1960
    - Rules, 1957
    - Western trip, 1958
    - Women's conferences, Washington, D.C., 1958-1960, (2 folders)
  - Democratic Party, 1961-1972
  - Democratic Party political contributions, 1963-1967
  - Democratic Woman of the Year contest, 1959-1960 (Box 14)
  - Drexel Institute of Technology, Philadelphia, Pa., 1964
  - Federal Women's Award
    - Correspondence, 1961-1972, (9 folders)
    - Printed matter and background material, 1961-1968, (8 folders) (Box 15)
    - Speech cards, 1963-1967
    - Study group on careers for women, 1966-1968 See also Classified (Box 16)
  - First Lady's Committee for a Beautiful Capital
    - 1964-1966, May, (9 folders)
    - 1966, July-1968, (10 folders) (Box 17)
    - 1969-1973, (4 folders) (Box 18)
  - Fisk University, Nashville, Tenn., 1968-1972, (2 folders)
  - Franklin Pierce College, Rindge, N.H., 1967
  - Gandhi, Indira, state visits, 1961-1966 See also Classified, (2 folders)
  - Harris, Patricia, 1965-1966
  - Highway Beautification Act, 1965
  - Hirose, Katsuyo, state visit, 1965
  - Humphrey, Hubert H., 1962-1971 See also Container 5, same heading
  - Inaugurations (Box 19)
    - 1961
      - Hospitality Committee, 1961-1963
      - Inaugural Committee report
      - Letters of appreciation
      - Lists
        - Invitations
        - Miscellaneous
      - Printed matter
    - 1965
  - Inter-American Commission of Women, Organization of American States, 1966-1968
  - Interior Department, report on beautification, 1965
  - John F. Kennedy Center for the Performing Arts, Washington, D.C., 1962-1971
  - Johnson, Lady Bird See also Container 5, same heading (Box 20)
    - Clippings and printed matter, 1964-1970, (2 folders)
    - Correspondence concerning, 1961-1974 See also Classified
    - HemisFair opening, San Antonio, Tex., 1968
    - Ladies of the Senate tribute, 1966
    - Speeches and press releases, 1962-1968, (4 folders)
    - Trip to Campobello Island, New Brunswick, Canada, 1964
    - "Whistle Stop" campaign, regional data, 1964 (Box 21)
    - Young Women's Christian Association convention, Cleveland, Ohio, 1964
  - Johnson, Lyndon B. See also Container 5, same heading
    - Correspondence concerning, 1966-1973
    - Latin American ambassadors' visit, San Antonio, Tex., 1967
    - Lyndon Baines Johnson Library, Austin, Tex., 1969-1973
    - Memorial service, Washington, D.C., 1973
    - Printed matter, 1963-1973
    - Speeches and remarks, 1964-1968, undated
  - Kennedy, John F. See also Container 6, same heading
    - Draft letters of appreciation for campaign, 1960
    - Letters of condolence on assassination, 1963-1964
    - Printed matter, 1961-1963
  - Labor's League for Political Education, 1951-1952
  - Lane Bryant Volunteer Awards, 1966-1971
  - Library of Congress, Music Division, 1966-1969
  - National Center of Education in Politics, board of trustees (Box 22)
    - Correspondence, 1961-1966
    - Printed matter, 1963-1966, (2 folders)